[Music]
hi my name is Kenny paban and in this
2024 release Wave 2 video we're going to
talk about report layout in general so
life cycle of layouts Telemetry and a
few more things like fonts so let's get
started in this
section we're going to talk about some
new actions you got on the report
layouts page get custom XML for word
create a new empty layout and also how
to update layouts with latest metadata
so let me show you what this is about so
in business Central I will just quickly
navigate to report layout page here we
go and you notice if you've been here
before that there are a few new actions
first first of all let's take the
scenario where your customer comes with
a Word document for how they would like
their sales invoice to look but that
word document doesn't have the word
metadata with the with the report fields
and so on so how can you uh how can you
come about that let's uh just find sales
invoice and uh this report
1306 if I
pick on up here in the menu the export
report schema this is a new action if I
click this I will get an XML file
downloaded now let's go and see how we
can inject this metadata into the word
document from our customer so here in
word
I let's just pretend that we use this
template invoice template maybe they
just like that invoice from office and
they this they say this is kind of how
we would like our invoice to look like
and um then we would like to map our
report fields to this layout the way to
do that is open the developer menu and
open the XML mapping Pane and you notice
here that we don't have the report
definition yet but we can now click add
new
part and uh get to the
document that we downloaded let's just
try downloads here and find that XML we
just got from business Central and if we
go back here now we have our standard
sales
invoice data set report metadata from
business Central and we're ready to map
this to um to the document so that was
the first use case of getting the the
XML word from business Central that you
can start from scratch with a Word
document and then upload that to
business
Central the second thing is what if you
already have a report but you would like
to have a new layout for that report in
Word Excel and so on how do you do that
well let's just pick the general journal
test report here and if I choose new up
here as the action I can uh maybe I can
just give it a name let's say
word
layout and I would like to create a new
word layout and I can I can now choose
this option create a blank layout from
the report object I could also make an
Excel or ADL layout from this and click
okay and now I have my word layout if I
export
this and open it open the word
file I now have
um if I go to developer tab and open XML
pane I now have the general journal
metadata and I can start writing my
report let's say that you have an app
that with some layout and you would like
to create a new one uh this can get you
started with an empty layout the last
the third demo is about updating a
layout with recent metadata so the
scenario is that you have a layout in
here but maybe someone added a report
extension that adds more to the data set
um how how do you then get your layout
updated with the recent version of the
metadata well there's a new action here
that says uh update and Export layout
where you simply choose this and now you
get a copy of uh of this layout injected
with the lay latest
metadata here's a neat little trick we
added to the Excel layout feature if you
ever tried to look up things from uh the
request
metadata tab in uh in Excel you quickly
get into writing formulas like this one
xook up company name blah blah blah and
no one loves writing these they're
complicated so we tried to make this a
little better or a little easier with
what we call named formulas let me show
you how to do
that all right so here in business
Central I will choose Excel reports and
just pick any of the preview reports
that we added in the last wave maybe
it's a customer top
10 and I will say which customer I want
maybe I I I just want all my customers
that's fine download it and here we get
it in Excel I can open it up
I will need to enable the content
because we use power
query right so here you can see I have
my top customer list this is just a
title but if you look up here you can
see that the Kronos USA is a very
complicated vook up
formula um so Kronos USA is just hiding
down here if I unhide all my worksheets
and just pick aggregated
metadata you can see the company name is
here on the requests property down here
Kronos us us this is these are all the
values that came when I ran the report
and um I would just like to get to this
but I don't like to write a v look up or
X look up like that so instead I can
simply say equals and then I can say
report request page
and I can say company
name there you go and now you have krona
USA as report request. compan name so
hopefully this will save you a lot of
time when you write your reports
anything you need to pick from the
aggregated metadata worksheet is
something you can simply use with these
named formulas where do they hide if I
go to formulas and go to name manager
you can see all of them here
that uh all these named formulas are
just synonyms for these complicated X
lookups so that's what named formulas is
all
about in this release wave we also added
life cycle Telemetry for report layout
changes on the report layouts page so
you now get Telemetry when a user
changed the default layout if they
change layout properties if they export
replace or delete a layout and you can
see all the event IDs in provines
here if you want to do your own kql
samples or try to analyze this Telemetry
this URL here
aka.ms slbc Telemetry samples is where
we normally have kql samples on our BCT
Tech repo and there's a new s Le file
here report layout life cycle. kql so
you can try out this Telemetry
yourself this silly last section with
the title all the little things we now
did to make General reporting easier
I'll just mention three things you can
set the report file name within an event
if you use vs code there's a new snippet
and then we have some methods that are
going to be obsoleted and I'll show you
talk about that so in case you want to
set the file name for reports that are
downloaded there's a new event in town
called onet file name and you simply uh
subscribe to that and and then you can
set uh the file name um in your in your
um event
subscriber the second thing is if you
use vs code there's a new snippet for
data link item called or data item so
you just say t data item or and then you
get it
there and the last is that we're going
to deprecate report. word layout rdlc
layout and Excel layout because these
don't make any sense anymore in a world
where a report can have multiple layouts
so if you rely on these you should move
your layout to the rendering section in
the report object um and then yeah
because you simply can't rely on a
report having only one of each of these
all right that's all we have about
document layouts and Reporting in
general but if you're more interested in
diving into the new cool things with
with word check out this video where
we'll go much more into details about
the new word adding and all the new
things you can do if you lay out your
documents with word thank you